<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div>
    <body>
        <heading>CHAP. VII. An Account of an Expedition to discover the inland Part of the Country,
            and our other Transactions, till we quitted the Island to continue our Voyage.</heading>
        <pb id="472"/>
        <p>AFTER the mate came on board, [day Saturday 25] he gave me a written account of his
            expedition, to the following effect:</p>
        <p>"At four o'clock in the morning, of Saturday the 25th of June, I landed, with four
            midshipmen, a serjeant and twelve marines, and twenty-four seamen, all armed, besides
            four who carried hatchets and other articles of traffick, and four who were loaded with
            ammunition and provisions, the rest being left with the boat: every man had his day's
            allowance of brandy, and the hatchet men two small kegs, to give out when I should think
            proper.</p>
        <p>"As soon as I got on shore, I called upon our old man, and took him with us: we then
            followed the course of the river in two parties, one marching on each side. For the
            first two miles it flowed through a valley of considerable width, in which were many
            habitations, with gardens walled in, and abundance of hogs, poultry, and fruit; the soil
            here seemed to be a rich fat earth, and was of a blackish colour. After this the valley
            became very narrow, and the ground rising abruptly on one side of the river, we were all
            obliged to march on the other. Where the stream was precipitated from the hills,
            channels had been cut to lead the water into gardens and plantations of fruit trees: in
            these gardens we found an herb which had never been brought down to the <pb id="473"/>
            water-side, and which we perceived the inhabitants eat raw. [day Saturday 25] I tasted
            it, and found it pleasant, its flavour somewhat re|sembling that of the West Indian
            spinnage, called Calleloor, though its leaf was very different. The ground was fenced
            off so as to make a very pretty appearance; the bread-fruit and apple trees were planted
            in rows on the declivity of the hills, and the cocoa nut and plantain, which require
            more moisture, on the level ground: under the trees, both on the sides and at the foot
            of the hills, there was very good grass, but no underwood. As we advanced, the windings
            of the stream became innumerable, the hills on each side swelled into mountains, and
            vast crags every where projected over our heads. Travelling now became difficult, and
            when we had proceeded about four miles, the road for the last mile having been very bad,
            we sat down to rest ourselves, and take the refreshment of our breakfast; we ranged
            our|selves upon the ground under a large apple tree, in a very pleasant spot; but just
            as we were about to begin our repast, we were suddenly alarmed by a confused sound of
            many voices, and a great shouting, and presently afterwards saw a multitude of men,
            women, and children upon the hill above us; our old man seeing us rise hastily, and look
            to our arms, beckoned to us to sit still, and immediately went up to the people that had
            surprised us. As soon as he joined them they were silent, and soon after disappeared; in
            a short time, however, they returned, and brought with them a large hog ready roasted,
            with plenty of bread-fruit, yams, and other refreshments, which they gave to the old
            man, who distributed them among our people. In return for this treat, I gave them some
            nails, buttons, and other things, with which they were greatly delighted. After this we
            proceeded up the valley as far as we could, searching all the runs of water, and all the
            places where water had run, for <pb id="474"/> appearances of metal or ore, [day
            Saturday 25] but could find none, except what I have brought back with me. I shewed all
            the people that we met with, the piece of saltpetre which had been picked up in the
            island, and which I had taken with me for that purpose, but none of them took any notice
            of it, nor could I learn from them any thing about it. The old man began now to be
            weary, and there being a mountain before us, he made signs that he would go home: before
            he left us, however, he made the people who had so liberally supplied us with
            provisions, take the baggage, with the fruit that had not been eaten, and some cocoa
            nut-shells full of fresh water, and made signs that they should follow us up the side of
            the mountain. As soon as he was gone, they gathered green branches from the neighbouring
            trees, and with many ceremonies, of which we did not know the meaning, laid them down
            before us: after this they took some small berries with which they painted themselves
            red, and the bark of a tree that contained a yellow juice, with which they stained their
            garments in different parts. We began to climb the mountain while our old man was still
            in sight, and he, perceiving that we made our way with difficulty through the weeds and
            brush-wood, which grew very thick, turned back, and said something to the natives in a
            firm loud tone; upon which twenty or thirty of the men went before us, and cleared us a
            very good path; they also re|freshed us with water and fruit as we went along, and
            assisted us to climb the most difficult places, which we should otherwise have found
            altogether impracticable. We began to ascend this hill at the distance of about six
            miles from the place where we landed, and I reckoned the top of it to be near a mile
            above the river that runs through the valley below. When we arrived at the summit, we
            again sat down to rest and refresh ourselves. While we were <pb id="475"/> climbing we
            flattered ourselves that from the top we should command the whole island, [day Saturday
            25] but we now saw mountains before us so much higher than our situation, that with
            respect to them we appeared to be in a valley; towards the ship indeed the view was
            enchanting: the sides of the hills were beautifully clothed with wood, villages were
            every where interspersed, and the vallies between them afforded a still richer prospect;
            the houses stood thicker, and the ver|dure was more luxuriant. We saw very few
            habitations above us, but discovered smoke in many places ascending from between the
            highest hills that were in sight, and there|fore I conjecture that the most elevated
            parts of the country are by no means without inhabitants. As we ascended the mountain,
            we saw many springs gush from fissures on the side of it, and when we had reached the
            summit, we found many houses that we did not discover as we passed them. No part of
            these mountains is naked; the summits of the highest that we could see were crowned with
            wood, but of what kind I know not: those that were of the same height with that which we
            had climbed, were woody on the sides, but on the summit were rocky and covered with
            fern. Upon the flats that appeared below these, there grew a sedgy kind of grass and
            weeds: in general the soil here, as well as in the valley, seemed to be rich. We saw
            several bushes of sugar-cane, which was very large and very good, growing wild, without
            the least culture. I likewise found ginger and turmerick, and have brought samples of
            both, but could not procure seeds of any tree, most of them being in blossom. After
            traversing the top of this mountain to a good distance, I found a tree exactly like a
            fern, except that it was 14 or 15 feet high. This tree I cut down, and found the in|side
            of it also like a fern: I would have brought a piece of it with me, but found it too
            cumbersome, and I knew not <pb id="476"/> what difficulties we might meet with before we
            got back to the ship, [day Saturday 25] which we judged to be now at a great distance.
            After having again recruited our strength by refreshment and rest, we began to descend
            the mountain, being still attended by the people to whose care we had been recom|mended
            by our old man. We kept our general direction to|wards the ship, but sometimes deviated
            a little to the right and left in the plains and vallies, when we saw any houses that
            were pleasantly situated, the inhabitants being every where ready to accommodate us with
            whatever they had. We saw no beast, except a few hogs, nor any birds, ex|cept parrots,
            parroquets, and green doves; by the river, however, there was plenty of ducks, and every
            place that was planted and cultivated, appeared to flourish with great luxuriance,
            though in the midst of what had the appearance of barren ground. I planted the stones of
            peaches, cherries, and plums, with a great variety of garden seeds, where I thought it
            was most probable that they would thrive, and limes, lemons, and oranges, in situations
            which resembled those in which they are found in the West Indies. In the afternoon, we
            arrived at a very pleasant spot, within about three miles of the ship, where we procured
            two hogs and some fowls, which the natives dressed for us very well, and with great
            expedition. Here we continued till the cool of the evening, and then made the best of
            our way for the ship, having liberally rewarded our guides, and the people who had
            provided us so good a dinner. Our men behaved through the whole day with the greatest
            decency and order, and we parted with our Indian friends in perfect good-hu|mour with
            each other."</p>
        <p>About 10 o'clock, [day Sunday 26] the next morning, the queen came on board according to
            her promise, with a present of hogs and fowls, but went on shore again soon afterwards.
            This day, <pb id="477"/> the Gunner sent off near thirty hogs, [day Sunday 26] with
            great plenty of fowls and fruit. We completed our wood and water, and got all ready for
            sea. More inhabitants came down to the beach, from the inland country, than we had seen
            before, and many of them appeared, by the respect that was paid them, to be of a
            superior rank. About three o'clock in the afternoon, the queen came again down to the
            beach, very well dressed, and followed by a great number of people. Having crossed the
            river with her attendants and our old man, she came once more on board the ship. She
            brought with her some very fine fruit, and renewed her solicitation, that I would stay
            ten days longer, with great earnestness, intimating that she would go into the country,
            and bring me plenty of hogs, fowls, and fruit. I endeavoured to ex|press a proper sense
            of her kindness and bounty, but assured her that I should certainly sail the next
            morning. This, as usual, threw her into tears, and after she recovered, she en|quired by
            signs when I should return: I endeavoured to ex|press fifty days, and she made signs for
            thirty: but the sign for fifty being constantly repeated, she seemed satisfied. She
            stayed on board till night, and it was then with the greatest difficulty that she could
            be prevailed upon to go on shore. When she was told that the boat was ready, she threw
            herself down upon the arm-chest, and wept a long time with an excess of passion that
            could not be pacified; at last, however, though with the greatest reluctance, she went
            into the boat, and was followed by her attendants and the old man. The old man had often
            intimated that his son, a lad about fourteen years of age, should go with us, and the
            boy seemed to be willing: he had, however, now disappeared for two days; I enquired
            after him when I first missed him, and the old man gave me to understand that he was
            gone into the country to see his friends, and would return time <pb id="478"/> enough to
            go with us; [day Sunday 26] but I have reason to think that, when the time drew near,
            the father's courage failed, and that to keep his child he secreted him till the ship
            was gone, for we never saw him afterwards.</p>
        <p>At break of day, on Monday the 27th, [day Monday 27] we unmoored, and at the same time I
            sent the barge and cutter to fill the few water-casks that were now empty. When they
            came near the shore, they saw, to their great surprise, the whole beach covered with
            inhabitants, and having some doubt whether it would be prudent to venture themselves
            among such a mul|titude, they were about to pull back again for the ship. As soon as
            this was perceived from the shore, the queen came forward, and beckoned them; at the
            same time guessing the reason of what had happened, she made the natives retire to the
            other side of the river: the boats then proceeded to the shore, and filled the casks, in
            the mean time she put some hogs and fruit on board, and when they were putting off would
            fain have returned with them to the ship. The offi|cer, however, who had received orders
            to bring off none of the natives, would not permit her; upon which she presently
            launched a double canoe, and was rowed off by her own people. Her canoe was immediately
            followed by fifteen or sixteen more, and all of them came up to the ship. The queen came
            on board, but not being able to speak, she sat down and gave vent to her passion by
            weeping. After she had been on board about an hour, a breeze springing up, we weighed
            anchor and made sail. Finding it now necessary to return into her canoe, she embraced us
            all in the most affectionate manner, and with many tears; all her attend|ants also
            expressed great sorrow at our departure. Soon after it fell calm, and I sent the boats
            a-head to tow, upon which all the canoes returned to the ship, and that which had the
            queen on board came up to the gun-room port, where her <pb id="479"/> people made it
            fast. [day Monday 27] In a few minutes she came into the bow of her canoe, where she sat
            weeping with inconsolable sorrow. I gave her many things which I thought would be of
            great use to her, and some for ornament; she silently ac|cepted of all, but took little
            notice of any thing. About 10 o'clock we were got without the reef, and a fresh breeze
            springing up, our Indian friends, and particularly the queen, once more bade us farewel,
            with such tenderness of affec|tion and grief, as filled both my heart and my eyes.</p>
        <p>At noon, the harbour from which we sailed bore S. E. ½ E. distant about twelve miles. It
            lies in latitude 17° 30′ S. lon|gitude 150° W. and I gave it the name of Port Royal
            Har|bour.</p>
    </body>
</div>
