<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
    <div type="chapter">
        <heading>CHAP. V. An Account of the Discovery of King George the Third's Island, or
            Otaheite, and of several Incidents which hap|pened both on board the Ship, and on
            Shore.</heading>
        <pb id="433"/>
        <p>AT two o'clock, the same day, we bore away, [day Thursday 18] and in about half an hour,
            discovered very high land in the W. S. W. At seven in the evening, Osnaburgh Island bore
            E. N. E. and the new discovered land, from W. N. W. to W. by S. As the weather was thick
            and squally, we brought to for the night, or at least till the fog should break away. At
            two in the morning, it being very clear, we made sail again; [day Friday 19] at
            day-break we saw the land, at about five leagues distance, and steered directly for it;
            but at eight o'clock, when we were close under it, the fog obliged us again to lie to,
            and when it cleared away, we were much surprised to find our|selves surrounded by some
            hundreds of canoes. They were of different sizes, and had on board different numbers,
            from one to ten, so that in all of them together, there could not be less than eight
            hundred people. When they came within pistol shot of the ship, they lay by, gazing at us
            with great astonishment, and by turns conferring with each other. In the mean time we
            shewed them trinkets of various kinds, and invited them on board. Soon after, they drew
            together, and held a kind of council, to determine what should be done: then they all
            paddled round the ship, making signs of friendship, and one of them holding up a branch
            of the plantain tree, made a speech that lasted near a quarter of an <pb id="434"/>hour,
            [day Friday 19] and then threw it into the sea. Soon after, as we continued to make
            signs of invitation, a fine, stout, lively young man ventured on board: he came up by
            the mizen chains, and jumped out of the shrouds upon the top of the awning. We made
            signs to him to come down upon the quarter-deck, and handed up some trinkets to him: he
            looked pleased, but would accept of nothing till some of the Indians came along side,
            and after much talk, threw a few branches of plantain tree on board the ship. He then
            ac|cepted our presents, and several others very soon came on board, at different parts
            of the ship, not knowing the proper entrance. As one of these Indians was standing near
            the gang-way, on the larboard side of the quarter-deck, one of our goats butted him upon
            the haunches: being surprised at the blow, he turned hastily about, and saw the goat
            raised upon his hind-legs, ready to repeat the blow. The appear|ance of this animal, so
            different from any he had ever seen, struck him with such terror, that he instantly
            leaped over board; and all the rest, upon seeing what had happened, followed his example
            with the utmost precipitation: they recovered however, in a short time, from their
            fright, and returned on board. After having a little reconciled them to our goats and
            sheep, I shewed them our hogs and poultry, and they immediately made signs that they had
            such ani|mals as these. I then distributed trinkets and nails among them, and made signs
            that they should go on shore and bring us some of their hogs, fowls and fruit, but they
            did not seem to understand my meaning: they were, in the mean time, watching an
            opportunity to steal some of the things that happened to lie in their way, but we
            generally detected them in the attempt. At last, however, one of the midshipmen happened
            to come where they were standing, with a new laced hat upon his head, and began to talk
            to <pb id="435"/>one of them by signs: while he was thus engaged, [day Friday 19]
            another of them came behind him, and suddenly snatching off the hat, leaped over the
            taffarel into the sea, and swam away with it. </p>
        <p>As we had no anchorage here, we stood along the shore, sending the boats at the same time
            to sound at a less distance. As none of these canoes had sails, they could not keep up
            with us, and therefore soon paddled back towards the shore. The country has the most
            delightful and roman|tic appearance that can be imagined: towards the sea it is level,
            and is covered with fruit trees of various kinds, par|ticularly the cocoa nut. Among
            these are the houses of the inhabitants, consisting only of a roof, and at a distance
            having greatly the appearance of a long barn. The country within, at about the distance
            of three miles, rises into lofty hills, that are crowned with wood, and terminate in
            peaks, from which large rivers are precipitated into the sea. We saw no shoals, but
            found the island skirted by a reef of rocks, through which there are several openings
            into deep water. About three o'clock in the afternoon, we brought to, a-breast of a
            large bay, where there was an appearance of anchorage. The boats were immediately sent
            to sound it, and while they were thus employed, I observed a great number of canoes
            gather round them. I suspected that the Indians had a design to attack them, and as I
            was very desirous to prevent mischief, I made the signal for the boats to come aboard,
            and at the same time, to intimidate the Indians, I fired a nine pounder over their
            heads. As soon as the cutter began to stand towards the ship, the Indians in their
            canoes, though they had been startled by the thunder of our nine pounder, endeavoured to
            cut her off. The boat, however, sailing faster than the canoes could paddle, soon got
            clear of those that were about her; but some others, that <pb id="436"/>were full of
            men, [day Friday 19] way-laid her in her course, and threw several stones into her,
            which wounded some of the people. Upon this, the officer on board fired a musquet,
            loaded with buck-shot, at the man who threw the first stone, and wounded him in the
            shoulder. The rest of the people in the canoes, as soon as they perceived their
            companion wounded, leapt into the sea, and the other canoes paddled away, in great
            terror and confusion. As soon as the boats reached the ship, they were hoisted on board,
            and just as she was about to stand on, we observed a large canoe, under sail, making
            after us. As I thought she might have some Chief on board, or might have been dispatched
            to bring me a message from some Chief, I determined to wait for her. She sailed very
            fast, and was soon along side of the ship, but we did not observe among those on board,
            any one that seemed to have an authority over the rest. One of them, however, stood up,
            and having made a speech, which con|tinued about five minutes, threw on board a branch
            of the plantain tree. We understood this to be a token of peace, and we returned it, by
            handing over one of the branches of plantain that had been left on board by our first
            visitors: with this and some toys, that were afterwards presented to him, he appeared to
            be much gratified, and after a short time, went away.</p>
        <p>The officers who had been sent out with the boats, in|formed me that they had sounded
            close to the reef, and found as great a depth of water as at the other islands:
            how|ever, as I was now on the weather side of the island, I had reason to expect
            anchorage in running to leeward. I therefore took this course, but finding breakers that
            ran off to a great distance from the south-end of the island, I hauled the wind, and
            continued turning to windward all night, in order to run down on the east side of the
            island.</p>
        <pb id="437"/>
        <p>At five o'clock in the morning, we made sail, [day Saturday 20] the land bearing N. W. by
            W. distant 10 leagues; and there seemed to be land five leagues beyond it, to the N. E.;
            a re|markable peak, like a sugar loaf, bore N. N. E. when we were about two leagues from
            the shore, which afforded a most delightful prospect, and was full of houses and
            inha|bitants. We saw several large canoes near the shore, under sail, but they did not
            steer towards the ship. At noon, we were within two or three miles of the island, and it
            then bore from S. ¾ W. to N. W. by W. We continued our course along the shore, sometimes
            at the distance of half a mile, and sometimes at the distance of four or five miles, but
            hitherto had got no soundings. At six o'clock in the evening, we were a-breast of a fine
            river, and the coast having a better appearance here than in any other part that we had
            seen, I determined to stand off and on all night, and try for anchor|age in the morning.
            As soon as it was dark, we saw a great number of lights all along the shore. At
            day-break, [day Sunday 21] we sent out the boats to sound, and soon after, they made the
            signal for 20 fathom. This produced an universal joy, which it is not easy to describe,
            and we immediately ran in, and came to an anchor in 17 fathom, with a clear sandy
            bottom. We lay about a mile distant from the shore, oppo|site to a fine run of water;
            the extreams of the land bearing from E. S. E. to N. W. by W. As soon as we had secured
            the ship, I sent the boats to sound along the coast, and look at the place where we saw
            the water. At this time, a con|siderable number of canoes came off to the ship, and
            brought with them hogs, fowls, and fruit in great plenty, which we purchased for
            trinkets and nails. But when the boats made towards the shore, the canoes, most of which
            were double, and very large, sailed after them. At first they kept at a distance, but as
            the boats approached the <pb id="438"/>shore, [day Sunday 21] they grew bolder, and at
            last three of the largest ran at the cutter, staved in her quarter, and carried away her
            out-rigger, the Indians preparing at the same time to board her, with their clubs and
            paddles in their hands. Our people being thus pressed, were obliged to fire, by which
            one of the assailants was killed, and another much wounded. Upon receiving the shot,
            they both fell overboard, and all the people who were in the same canoe, instantly
            leaped into the sea after them: the other two canoes dropped a-stern, and our boats went
            on without any farther interrup|tion. As soon as the Indians, who were in the water, saw
            that the boats stood on without attempting to do them any farther hurt, they recovered
            their canoe, and hauled in their wounded companions. They set them both upon their feet
            to see if they could stand, and finding they could not, they tried whether they could
            sit upright: one of them could, and him they supported in that posture, but perceiv|ing
            that the other was quite dead, they laid the body along at the bottom of the canoe.
            After this some of the canoes went ashore, and others returned again to the ship to
            traffick, which is a proof that our conduct had convinced them that while they behaved
            peaceably they had nothing to fear, and that they were conscious they had brought the
            mischief which had just happened upon themselves.</p>
        <p>The boats continued sounding till noon, when they re|turned with an account that the
            ground was very clear; that it was at the depth of five fathom, within a quarter of a
            mile of the shore, but that there was a very great surf where we had seen the water. The
            officers told me, that the inhabitants swarmed upon the beach, and that many of them
            swam off to the boat with fruit, and bamboos filled with water. They said that they were
            very importunate with them to come on shore, particularly the women, who came down to
            the <pb id="439"/>beach, and stripping themselves naked, [day Sunday 21] endeavoured to
            allure them by many wanton gestures, the meaning of which could not possibly be
            mistaken. At this time, however, our people resisted the temptation.</p>
        <p>In the afternoon, I sent the boats again to the shore, with some barecas, or small casks,
            which are filled at the head, and have a handle by which they are carried, to endeavour
            to procure some water, of which we began to be in great want. In the mean time, many of
            the canoes continued about the ship, but the Indians had been guilty of so many thefts,
            that I would not suffer any more of them to come on board.</p>
        <p>At five in the evening, the boats returned with only two barecas of water, which the
            natives had filled for them; and as a compensation for their trouble, they thought fit
            to detain all the rest. Our people, who did not leave their boat, tried every expedient
            they could think of to induce the Indians to return their water vessels, but without
            success; and the Indians, in their turn, were very pressing for our people to come on
            shore, which they thought it prudent to decline. There were many thousands of the
            inhabitants of both sexes, and a great number of children on the beach, when our boats
            came away.</p>
        <p>The next morning, [day Monday 22] I sent the boats on shore again for water, with nails,
            hatchets, and such other things as I thought most likely to gain the friendship of the
            inhabitants. In the mean time, a great number of canoes came off to the ship, with
            bread-fruit*, plantains, a fruit resembling an apple only better, fowls, and hogs, which
            we purchased with beads, nails, knives, and other articles of the like kind, so <pb
                id="440"/>that we procured pork enough to serve the ship's company two days, [day
            Monday 22] at a pound a man. </p>
        <p>When the boats returned, they brought us only a few calibashes of water, for the number
            of people on the beach was so great, that they would not venture to land, though the
            young women repeated the allurements which they had practised the day before, with still
            more wanton, and, if possible, less equivocal gestures. Fruit and provisions of various
            kinds were brought down and ranged upon the beach, of which our people were also invited
            to partake, as an additional inducement for them to leave the boat. They continued,
            however, inexorable, and shewing the Indians the barecas on board, made signs that they
            should bring down those which had been detained the day before: to this the Indians were
            inexorable in their turn, and our people therefore weighed their grapplings, and sounded
            all round the place, to see whether the ship could come in near enough to cover the
            waterers, in which case they might venture on shore, in defiance of the whole island.
            When they put off, the women pelted them with apples and bananas, shouting, and shewing
            every mark of derision and contempt that they could devise. They reported, that the ship
            might ride in four fathom water, with sandy ground, at two cables' length from the
            shore, and in five fathom water at three cables' length. The wind here blew right along
            the shore, raising a great surf on the side of the vessel, and on the beach.</p>
        <p>At day-break, [day Tuesday 23] the next morning, we weighed, with a design to anchor off
            the watering-place. As we were stand|ing off, to get farther to windward, we discovered
            a bay about six or eight miles to leeward, over the land, from the <pb id="441"
            />mast-head, and immediately bore away for it, [day Tuesday 23] sending the boats a-head
            to sound. At nine o'clock, the boats making the signal for 12 fathom, we hauled round a
            reef, and stood in, with a design to come to an anchor; but when we came near the boats,
            one of which was on each bow, the ship struck. Her head continued immoveable, but her
            stern was free; and, upon casting the lead, we found the depth of water, upon the reef
            or shoal, to be from 17 fathom to two and a half: we clewed all up as fast as possible,
            and cleared the ship of what lumber there happened to be upon the deck, at the same time
            getting out the long-boat, with the stream and kedge anchors, the stream cable and
            hauser, in order to carry them without the reef, that when they had taken ground, the
            ship might be drawn off towards them, by applying a great force to the capstern, but
            unhappily without the reef we had no bottom. Our condition was now very alarming, the
            ship continued beating against the rock with great force, and we were surrounded by many
            hundred canoes, full of men: they did not, however, attempt to come on board us, but
            seemed to wait in ex|pectation of our shipwreck. In the anxiety and terror of such a
            situation we continued near an hour, without being able to do any thing for our
            deliverance, except staving some water casks in the fore-hold, when a breeze happily
            spring|ing up from the shore, the ship's head swung off. We immediately pressed her with
            all the sail we could make; upon which she began to move, and was very soon once more in
            deep water.</p>
        <p>We now stood off, and the boats being sent to leeward, found that the reef ran down to
            the westward about a mile and a half, and that beyond it there was a very good har|bour.
            The master, after having placed a boat at the end of the reef, and furnished the
            long-boat with anchor and hausers, <pb id="442"/>and a guard to defend her from an
            attack of the Indians, [day Tuesday 23] came on board, and piloted the ship round the
            reef into the harbour, where, about twelve o'clock, she came to an an|chor in 17 fathom
            water, with a fine bottom of black sand. </p>
        <p>The place where the ship struck appeared, upon farther examination, to be a reef of sharp
            coral rock, with very un|equal soundings, from six fathom to two; and it happened
            unfortunately to lie between the two boats that were placed as a direction to the ship,
            the weathermost boat having 12 fathom, and the leewardmost nine. The wind freshened
            almost as soon as we got off, and though it soon became calm again, the surf ran so
            high, and broke with such vio|lence upon the rock, that if the ship had continued fast
            half an hour longer, she must inevitably have been beaten to pieces. Upon examining her
            bottom, we could not dis|cover that she had received any damage, except that a small
            piece was beaten off the bottom of the rudder. She did not appear to admit any water,
            but the trussle-trees, at the head of all the masts, were broken short, which we
            supposed to have happened while she was beating against the rock. Our boats lost their
            grapplings upon the reef, but as we had reason to hope that the ship was sound, they
            gave us very little concern. As soon as the ship was secured, I sent the master, with
            all the boats manned and armed, to sound the upper part of the bay, that if he found
            good an|chorage we might warp the ship up within the reef, and anchor her in safety. The
            weather was now very pleasant, a great number of canoes were upon the reef, and the
            shore was crouded with people.</p>
        <p>About four in the afternoon the master returned, and reported, that there was every where
            good anchorage; I therefore determined to warp the ship up the bay early in <pb id="443"
            />the morning, and in the mean time, [day Tuesday 23] I put the people at four watches,
            one watch to be always under arms; loaded and primed all the guns, fixed musquetoons in
            all the boats, and ordered all the people who were not upon the watch, to re|pair to the
            quarters assigned them, at a moment's warning there being a great number of canoes, some
            of them very large, and full of men, hovering upon the shore, and many smaller venturing
            to the ship, with hogs, fowls, and fruit, which we purchased of them, much to the
            satisfaction of both parties; and at sun-set, all the canoes rowed in to the shore. </p>
        <p>At six o'clock the next morning, [day Wednes. 24] we began to warp the ship up the
            harbour, and soon after, a great number of canoes came under her stern. As I perceived
            that they had hogs, fowls, and fruit on board, I ordered the gunner, and two midshipmen,
            to purchase them for knives, nails, beads, and other trinkets, at the same time
            prohibiting the trade to all other persons on board. By eight o'clock, the number of
            canoes was greatly increased, and those that came last up were double, of a very large
            size, with twelve or fifteen stout men in each. I observed, with some concern, that they
            ap|peared to be furnished rather for war than trade, having very little on board except
            round pebble stones; I therefore sent for Mr. Furneaux, my first lieutenant being still
            very ill, and ordered him to keep the fourth watch constantly at their arms, while the
            rest of the people were warping the ship. In the mean time more canoes were continually
            coming off from the shore, which were freighted very dif|ferently from the rest, for
            they had on board a number of women who were placed in a row, and who, when they came
            near the ship, made all the wanton gestures that can be conceived. While these ladies
            were practising their al|lurements, the large canoes, which were freighted with <pb
                id="444"/>stones, [day Wednes. 24] drew together very close round the ship, some of
            the men on board singing in a hoarse voice, some blowing conchs, and some playing on a
            flute. After some time, a man who sat upon a canopy that was fixed on one of the large
            double canoes, made signs that he wished to come up to the ship's side; I immediately
            intimated my consent, and when he came along side, he gave one of the men a bunch of red
            and yellow feathers, making signs that he should carry it to me. I received it with
            expressions of amity, and immediately got some trinkets to present him in return, but to
            my great surprise he had put off to a little distance from the ship, and upon his
            throwing up the branch of a cocoa-nut tree, there was an universal shout from all the
            canoes, which at once moved towards the ship, and a shower of stones was poured into her
            on every side. As an attack was now begun, in which our arms only could render us
            supe|rior to the multitude that assailed us, especially as great part of the ship's
            company was in a sick and feeble condition, I ordered the guard to fire; two of the
            quarter-deck guns, which I had loaded with small shot, were also fired nearly at the
            same time, and the Indians appeared to be thrown into some confusion: in a few minutes,
            however, they renewed the attack, and all our people that were able to come upon deck,
            having by this time got to their quarters, I ordered them to fire the great guns, and to
            play some of them con|stantly at a place on shore, where a great number of canoes were
            still taking in men, and pushing off towards the ship with the utmost expedition. When
            the great guns began to fire, there were not less than three hundred canoes about the
            ship, having on board at least two thousand men; many thousands were also upon the
            shore, and more canoes coming from every quarter: the firing, however, soon drove away
            the canoes that were about the ship, and put a stop to the <pb id="445"/>coming off of
            others. [day Wednes. 24] As soon as I saw some of them re|treating, and the rest quiet,
            I ordered the firing to cease, hoping that they were sufficiently convinced of our
            superi|ority, not to renew the contest. In this, however, I was unhappily mistaken: a
            great number of the canoes that had been dispersed, soon drew together again, and lay
            some time on their paddles, looking at the ship from the distance of about a quarter of
            a mile, and then suddenly hoisting white streamers, pulled towards the ship's stern, and
            began again to throw stones, with great force and dexterity, by the help of slings, from
            a considerable distance: each of these stones weighed about two pounds, and many of them
            wounded the people on board, who would have suffered much more, if an awning had not
            been spread over the whole deck to keep out the sun, and the hammocks placed in the
            nettings. At the same time several canoes, well manned, were making towards the ship's
            bow, having probably taken notice that no shot had been fired from this part: I
            therefore ordered some guns forward, to be well pointed and fired at these canoes; at
            the same time running out two guns abaft, and pointing them well at the canoes that were
            making the attack. Among the canoes that were coming toward the bow, there was one which
            appeared to have some Chief on board, as it was by signals made from her, that the
            others had been called to|gether: it happened that a shot, fired from the guns for|ward,
            hit this canoe so full as to cut it asunder. As soon as this was observed by the rest,
            they dispersed with such haste that in half an hour there was not a single canoe to be
            seen; the people also who had crouded the shore, immediately fled over the hills with
            the utmost precipitation.</p>
        <p>Having now no reason to fear any further interruption, we warped the ship up the harbour,
            and by noon, we were <pb id="446"/>not more than half a mile from the upper part of the
            bay, [day Wednes. 24] within less than two cables' length of a fine river, and about two
            and a half of the reef. We had here nine fathom water, and close to the shore there were
            five. We moored the ship, and carried out the stream-anchor, with the two shroud
            hausers, for a spring, to keep the ship's broad-side a-breast of the river; we also got
            up and mounted the eight guns which had been put into the hold. As soon as this was
            done, the boats were employed in sounding all round the bay, and in examining the shore
            where any of the in|habitants appeared, in order to discover, whether it was pro|bable
            that they would give us any further disturbance. All the afternoon, [day Thursday 25]
            and part of the next morning, was spent in this service; and about noon, the master
            returned, with a tolerable survey of the place, and reported, that there were no canoes
            in sight; that there was good landing on every part of the beach; that there was nothing
            in the bay from which danger could be apprehended, except the reef, and some rocks at
            the upper end, which appeared above water; and that the river, though it emptied itself
            on the other side of the point, was fresh water.</p>
        <p>Soon after the master had brought me this account, I sent Mr. Furneaux again, with all
            the boats manned and armed, the marines being also put on board, with orders to land
            opposite to our station, and secure himself, under cover of the boats and the ship, in
            the clearest ground he could find. About two o'clock the boats landed without any
            opposition, and Mr. Furneaux stuck up a staff, upon which he hoisted a pendant, turned a
            turf, and took possession of the island in his Majesty's name, in honour of whom he
            called it KING GEORGE THE THIRD's ISLAND: he then went to the river, and tasted the
            water, which he found excellent, and mixing some of it with rum, every man drank his
            Majesty's health. <pb id="447"/>While he was at the river, [day Thursday 25] which was
            about twelve yards wide, and fordable, he saw two old men on the opposite side of it,
            who perceiving that they were discovered, put them|selves in a supplicatory posture, and
            seemed to be in great terror and confusion. Mr. Furneaux made signs that they should
            come over the river, and one of them complied. When he landed, he came forward, creeping
            upon his hands and knees, but Mr. Furneaux raised him up, and while he stood trembling,
            shewed him some of the stones that were thrown at the ship, and endeavoured to make him
            apprehend that if the natives attempted no mischief against us, we should do no harm to
            them. He ordered two of the water casks to be filled, to shew the Indian that we wanted
            water, and produced some hatchets, and other things, to intimate that he wished to trade
            for provisions. The old man, during this pantomimical conversation, in some degree
            recovered his spirits; and Mr. Furneaux, to confirm his professions of friendship, gave
            him a hatchet, some nails, beads, and other trifles; after which he reimbarked on board
            the boats, and left the pendant flying. As soon as the boats were put off, the old man
            went up to the pendant, and danced round it a considerable time: he then retired, but
            soon after re|turned with some green boughs, which he threw down, and retired a second
            time: it was not long, however, before he appeared again, with about a dozen of the
            inhabitants, and putting themselves in a supplicating posture, they all ap|proached the
            pendant in a slow pace, but the wind happening to move it, when they were got close to
            it, they suddenly retreated with the greatest precipitation. After standing some time at
            a distance, and gazing at it, they went away, but in a short time came back, with two
            large hogs alive, which they laid down at the foot of the staff, and at length taking
            courage, they began to dance. When they had per|formed <pb id="448"/>this ceremony, [day
            Thursday 25] they brought the hogs down to the water side, launched a canoe, and put
            them on board. The old man, who had a large white beard, then embarked with them alone,
            and brought them to the ship: when he came along side, he made a set speech, and
            afterwards handed in several green plantain leaves, one by one, uttering a sen|tence, in
            a solemn slow tone, with each of them as he de|livered it; after this he sent on board
            the two hogs, and then turning round, pointed to the land. I ordered some presents to be
            given him, but he would accept of nothing; and soon after put off his canoe, and went on
            shore.</p>
        <p>At night, soon after it was dark, we heard the noise of many drums, with conchs, and
            other wind instruments, and saw a multitude of lights all along the coast. [day Friday
            26] At six in the morning, seeing none of the natives on shore, and observing that the
            pendant was taken away, which probably they had learnt to despise, as the frogs in the
            fable did King Log, I ordered the lieutenant to take a guard on shore, and if all was
            well, to send off, that we might begin watering: in a short time I had the satisfaction
            to find that he had sent off for water casks, and by eight o'clock, we had four tons of
            water on board. While our people were employed in filling the casks, several of the
            natives appeared on the opposite side of the river, with the old man whom the officer
            had seen the day before; and soon after he came over, and brought with him a little
            fruit, and a few fowls, which were also sent off to the ship. At this time, having been
            very ill for near a fortnight, I was so weak that I could scarcely crawl about; however,
            I employed my glasses to see what was doing on shore. At near half an hour after eight
            o'clock, I perceived a multitude of the natives coming over a hill at about the distance
            of a mile, and at the same time a great number of canoes making round the western point,
            and <pb id="449"/>keeping close along the shore. [day Friday 26] I then looked at the
            water|ing-place, and saw at the back of it, where it was clear, a very numerous party of
            the natives creeping along behind the bushes; I saw also many thousands in the woods,
            push|ing along towards the watering-place, and canoes coming very fast round the other
            point of the bay to the eastward. Being alarmed at these appearances, I dispatched a
            boat, to acquaint the officer on shore with what I had seen, and order him immediately
            to come on board with his men, and leave the casks behind him: he had, however,
            discovered his danger, and embarked before the boat reached him. Having perceived the
            Indians that were creeping towards him under shelter of the wood, he immediately
            dispatch|ed the old man to them, making signs that they should keep at a distance, and
            that he wanted nothing but water. As soon as they perceived that they were discovered,
            they began to shout, and advanced with greater speed. The of|ficer immediately repaired
            to the boats with his people, and the Indians, in the mean time having crossed the
            river, took possession of the water casks, with great appearance of exulta|tion and joy.
            The canoes now pulled along the shore, to|wards the place, with the utmost expedition,
            all the people on land keeping pace with them, except a multitude of women and children,
            who seated themselves upon a hill which overlooked the bay and the beach. The canoes
            from each point of the bay, as they drew nearer to that part of it where the ship was at
            anchor, put on shore, and took in more men, who had great bags in their hands, which
            after|wards appeared to be filled with stones. All the canoes that had come round the
            points, and many others that had put off from the shore within the bay, now made towards
            the ship, so that I had no doubt but that they intended to try <pb id="450"/>their
            fortune in a second attack. [day Friday 26] As to shorten the contest would certainly
            lessen the mischief, I determined to make this action decisive, and put an end to
            hostilities at once; I therefore ordered the people, who were all at their quarters, to
            fire first upon the canoes which were drawn together in groups: this was immediately
            done so effectually, that those which were to the westward made towards the shore as
            fast as possible, and those to the eastward, getting round the reef, were soon beyond
            the reach of our guns. I then di|rected the fire into the wood in different parts, which
            soon drove the Indians out of it, who ran up the hill where the women and children had
            seated themselves to see the battle. Upon this hill there were now several thousands who
            thought themselves in perfect security; but to convince them of the contrary, and hoping
            that when they saw the shot fall much farther than they could think possible, they would
            suppose it could reach them at any distance, I ordered some of the guns to be let down
            as low as they would admit, and fired four shot towards them. Two of the balls fell
            close by a tree where a great number of these people were fitting, and struck them with
            such terror and consternation, that in less than two minutes not one of them was to be
            seen. Having thus cleared the coast, I manned and armed the boats, and putting a strong
            guard on board, I sent all the carpenters with their axes, and ordered them to destroy
            every canoe that had been run ashore. Before noon, this service was effectually
            performed, and more than fifty canoes, many of which were sixty feet long, and three
            broad, and lashed together, were cut to pieces. Nothing was found in them but stones and
            slings, except a little fruit, and a few fowls and hogs, which were on board two or
            three canoes of a much smaller size.</p>
        <pb id="451"/>
        <p>At two o'clock in the afternoon, [day Friday 26] about ten of the natives came out of the
            wood with green boughs in their hands, which they stuck up near the water side, and
            retired. After a short time, they appeared again, and brought with them several hogs,
            with their legs tied, which they placed near the green boughs, and retired a second
            time. After this they brought down several more hogs, and some dogs, with their fore
            legs tied over their heads, and going again into the woods, brought back several bundles
            of the cloth which they use for apparel, and which has some resemblance to Indian paper.
            These they placed upon the beach, and called to us on board to fetch them away. As we
            were at the distance of about three cables' length, we could not then perfectly discover
            of what this peace-offering consisted: we guessed at the hogs and the cloth, but seeing
            the dogs, with their fore legs appearing over the hinder part of the neck, rise up
            several times, and run a little way in an erect posture, we took them for some strange
            unknown animal, and were very impatient to have a nearer view of them. The boat was
            therefore sent on shore with all expedition, and our wonder was soon at an end. Our
            people found nine good hogs, besides the dogs and the cloth: the hogs were brought off,
            but the dogs were turned loose, and with the cloth left behind. In return for the hogs,
            our people left upon the shore some hatchets, nails, and other things, making signs to
            some of the Indians who were in sight, to take them away with their cloth. Soon after
            the boat had come on board, the Indians brought down two more hogs, and called to us to
            fetch them; the boat therefore returned, and fetched off the two hogs, but still left
            the cloth, though the Indians made signs that we should take it. Our people reported,
            that they had not touched any of the things which <pb id="452"/>they had left upon the
            beach for them, [day Friday 26] and somebody sug|gesting that they would not take our
            offering because we had not accepted their cloth, I gave orders that it should be
            fetched away. The event proved that the conjecture was true, for the moment the boat had
            taken the cloth on board, the Indians came down, and with every possible demonstra|tion
            of joy, carried away all I had sent them into the wood. Our boats then went to the
            watering-place, and filled and brought off all the casks, to the amount of about six
            tons. We found that they had suffered no injury while they had been in the possession of
            the Indians, but some leathern buckets and funnels which had been taken away with the
            casks, were not returned.</p>
        <p>The next morning I sent the boats on shore, [day Saturday 27] with a guard, to fill some
            more casks with water, and soon after the people were on shore, the same old man who had
            come over the river to them the first day, came again to the farther side of it, where
            he made a long speech, and then crossed the water. When he came up to the waterers, the
            officer shewed him the stones that were piled up like cannon balls upon the shore, and
            had been brought thither since our first landing, and some of the bags that had been
            taken out of the canoes which I had ordered to be destroyed, filled with stones, and
            endeavoured to make him understand that the Indians had been the aggressors, and that
            the mischief we had done them was in our own defence. The old man seemed to apprehend
            his meaning, but not to admit it: he immediately made a speech to the people, pointing
            to the stones, slings, and bags, with great emotion, and sometimes his looks, gestures,
            and voice were so furious as to be frightful. His passions, however, subsided by
            degrees, and the officer, who to his great regret could not understand one <pb id="453"
            />word of all that he had said, endeavoured to convince him, [day Saturday 27] by all
            the signs he could devise, that we wished to live in friendship with them, and were
            disposed to shew them every mark of kindness in our power. He then shook hands with him,
            and embraced him, giving him at the same time seve|ral such trinkets as he thought would
            be most acceptable. He contrived also to make the old man understand that we wished to
            traffick for provisions, that the Indians should not come down in great numbers, and
            that they should keep on one side of the river and we on the other. After this the old
            man went away with great appearance of satisfaction, and before noon a trade was
            established, which furnished us with hogs, fowls, and fruit in great abundance, so that
            all the ship's company, whether sick or well, had as much as they could use.</p>
    </div>
</body>
