<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div>
    <body>
        <heading>CHAP. VI. The Sick sent on Shore, and a regular Trade established with the Natives;
            some Account of their Character and Manners, of their Visits on board the Ship, and a
            Variety of Incidents that happened during this Inter|course.</heading>
        <pb id="454"/>
        <p>MATTERS being thus happily settled, [day Saturday 27] I sent the Sur|geon, with the
            Second Lieutenant, to examine the country, and fix upon some place where the sick might
            take up their residence on shore. When they returned, they said, that with respect to
            health and convenience, all the places that they had seen upon the island seemed to be
            equally proper; but that with respect to safety, they could recom|mend none but the
            watering-place, as they would be there under the protection of the ship and the guard,
            and would easily be prevented from straggling into the country, and brought off to their
            meals. To the watering-place therefore I sent them, with those that were employed in
            filling the casks, and appointed the gunner to command the party that was to be their
            guard. A tent was erected for them as a shelter both from the sun and the rain, and the
            Surgeon was sent to superintend their conduct, and give his advice if it should be
            wanted. It happened that walking out with his gun, after he had seen the sick properly
            disposed of in the tent, a wild duck flew over his head, which he shot, and it fell dead
            among some of the natives who were on the other side of the river. This threw them into
            a panic, and <pb id="455"/>they all ran away: [day Saturday 27] when they got to some
            distance they stopped, and he made signs to them to bring the duck over: this one of
            them at last ventured to do, and, pale and trem|bling, laid it down at his feet. Several
            other ducks happen|ing at the instant to fly over the spot where they were standing, he
            fired again, and fortunately brought down three more. This incident gave the natives
            such a dread of a gun, that if a musquet was pointed at a thousand of them, they would
            all run away like a flock of sheep; and probably the ease with which they were
            afterwards kept at a distance, and their orderly behaviour in their traffick, was in a
            great measure owing to their having upon this occasion seen the instrument of which
            before they had only felt the effects.</p>
        <p>As I foresaw that a private traffick would probably com|mence between such of our people
            as were on shore, and the natives, and that if it was left to their own caprice,
            perpetual quarrels and mischief would ensue, I ordered that all mat|ters of traffick
            should be transacted by the gunner, on behalf of both parties, and I directed him to see
            that no injury was done to the natives, either by violence or fraud, and by all possible
            means to attach the old man to his interest. This service he performed with great
            diligence and fidelity, nor did he neglect to complain of those who transgressed my
            orders, which was of infinite advantage to all parties; for as I punished the first
            offenders with a necessary severity, many irregularities, that would otherwise have
            produced the most disagreeable consequences, were prevented: we were also indebted for
            many advantages to the old man, whose cau|tion kept our people perpetually upon their
            guard, and soon brought back those who straggled from the party. The natives would
            indeed sometimes pilfer, but by the terror of a gun, without using it, he always found
            means to make them bring back what was stolen. A fellow had one day the <pb id="456"
            />dexterity and address to cross the river unperceived, [day Saturday 27] and steal a
            hatchet; the gunner, as soon as he missed it, made the old man understand what had
            happened, and got his party ready, as if he would have gone into the woods after the
            thief: the old man, however, made signs that he would save him the trouble, and
            immediately setting off, returned in a very short time with the hatchet. The gunner then
            insisted that the offender should be delivered up, and with this also the old man,
            though not without great reluctance, com|plied. When the fellow was brought down, the
            gunner knew him to be an old offender, and therefore sent him pri|soner on board. I had
            no intention to punish him otherwise, than by the fear of punishment, and therefore,
            after great entreaty and intercession, I gave him his liberty, and sent him on shore.
            When the natives saw him return in safety, it is hard to say whether their astonishment
            or joy was greatest; they received him with universal acclamations, and immediately
            carried him off into the woods: the next day, however, he returned, and as a
            propitiation to the gunner, he brought him a considerable quantity of bread-fruit, and a
            large hog, ready roasted.</p>
        <p>At this time, the people on board were employed in caulking and painting the
            weather-work, over-hauling the rigging, stowing the hold, and doing other necessary
            busi|ness, but my disorder, which was a bilious cholic, increased so much, that this day
            I was obliged to take to my bed; my First Lieutenant also still continued very ill, and
            the Purser was incapable of his duty. The whole command devolved upon Mr. Furneaux, the
            Second Lieutenant, to whom I gave general directions, and recommended a particular
            attention to the people on shore. I also ordered that fruit and fresh provisions should
            be served to the ship's company as long as they could be procured, and that the boats
            should never be <pb id="457"/>absent from the ship after sun-set. [day Saturday 27]
            These directions were fulfilled with such prudence and punctuality, that during all my
            sickness I was not troubled with any business, nor had the mortification to hear a
            single complaint or appeal. The men were constantly served with fresh pork, fowls, and
            fruit, in such plenty, that when I left my bed, after having been confined to it near a
            fortnight, my ship's company looked so fresh and healthy, that I could scarcely believe
            them to be the same people.</p>
        <p>Sunday the 28th was marked by no incident; [day Sunday 28] but on Mon|day the 29th, [day
            Monday 29] one of the gunner's party found a piece of saltpetre near as big as an egg.
            As this was an object of equal curiosity and importance, diligent enquiry was
            im|mediately made from whence it came. The surgeon asked every one of the people on
            shore, separately, whether he had brought it from the ship; every one on board also was
            asked whether he had carried it on shore, but all declared that they had never had such
            a thing in their possession. Appli|cation was then made to the natives, but the meaning
            of both parties was so imperfectly conveyed by signs, that nothing could be learnt of
            them about it: during our whole stay here, however, we saw no more than this one
            piece.</p>
        <p>While the gunner was trafficking for provisions on shore, we sometimes hauled the seine,
            but we caught no fish; we also frequently crawled, but with no better success: the
            dis|appointment, however, was not felt, for the produce of the island enabled our people
            to "fare sumptuously every day."</p>
        <p>All matters continued in the same situation till the 2d of July, when our old man being
            absent, [month July] [day Thursday 2] the supply of fresh provisions and fruit fell
            short; we had, however, enough to <pb id="458"/>serve most of the messes, reserving
            plenty for the sick and convalescent.</p>
        <p>On the 3d, [day Friday 3] we heeled the ship, and looked at her bottom, which we found as
            clean as when she came out of dock, and to our great satisfaction, as sound. During all
            this time, none of the natives came near our boats, or the ship, in their canoes. This
            day, about noon, we caught a very large shark, and when the boats went to fetch the
            people on board to dinner, we sent it on shore. When the boats were putting off again,
            the gunner seeing some of the natives on the other side of the river, beckoned them to
            come over; they immediately complied, and he gave them the shark, which they soon cut to
            pieces, and carried away with great appearance of satisfaction.</p>
        <p>On Sunday the 5th, [day Sunday 5] the old man returned to the market-tent, and made the
            gunner understand that he had been up the country, to prevail upon the people to bring
            down their hogs, poultry, and fruit, of which the parts near the water|ing-place were
            now nearly exhausted. The good effects of his expedition soon appeared, for several
            Indians, whom our people had never seen before, came in with some hogs that were larger
            than any that had been yet brought to market. In the mean time, the old man ventured off
            in his canoe, to the ship, and brought with him, as a present to me, a hog ready
            roasted. I was much pleased with his attention and liberality, and gave him, in return
            for his hog, an iron pot, a looking-glass, a drinking-glass, and several other things,
            which no man in the island was in possession of but himself.</p>
        <p>While our people were on shore, several young women were permitted to cross the river,
            who, though they were not averse to the granting of personal favours, knew the <pb
                id="459"/>value of them too well not to stipulate for a consideration: [day Sunday
            5] the price, indeed, was not great, yet it was such as our men were not always able to
            pay, and under this temptation they stole nails and other iron from the ship. The nails
            that we brought for traffick, were not always in their reach, and therefore they drew
            several out of different parts of the ves|sel, particularly those that fastened the
            cleats to the ship's side. This was productive of a double mischief; damage to the ship,
            and a considerable rise at market. When the gun|ner offered, as usual, small nails for
            hogs of a middling size, the natives refused to take them, and produced large spikes,
            intimating that they expected such nails as these. A most diligent enquiry was set on
            foot to discover the offenders, but all to no purpose; and though a large reward was
            offered to procure intelligence, none was obtained. I was mortified at the
            disappointment, but I was still more morti|fied at a fraud which I found some of our
            people had prac|tised upon the natives. When no nails were to be procured, they had
            stolen lead, and cut it up in the shape of nails. Many of the natives who had been paid
            with this base mo|ney, brought their leaden nails, with great simplicity, to the gunner,
            and requested him to give them iron in their stead. With this request, however
            reasonable, he could not com|ply; because, by rendering lead current, it would have
            en|couraged the stealing it, and the market would have been as effectually spoiled by
            those who could not procure nails, as by those who could; it was therefore necessary,
            upon every account, to render this leaden currency of no value, though for our honour I
            should have been glad to have called it in.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday the 7th, [day Tuesday 7] I sent one of the mates, with thirty men, to a
            village at a little distance from the market, hoping <pb id="460"/>that refreshments
            might there be bought at the original price; [day Tuesday 7] but here they were obliged
            to give still more than at the water-side. In the mean time, being this day able to get
            up for the first time, and the weather being fine, I went into a boat, and rowed about
            four miles down the coast. I found the country populous, and pleasant in the highest
            degree, and saw many canoes on the shore; but not one came off to us, nor did the people
            seem to take the least notice of us as we passed along. About noon I returned to the
            ship.</p>
        <p>The commerce which our men had found means to esta|blish with the women of the island,
            rendered them much less obedient to the orders that had been given for the regu|lation
            of their conduct on shore, than they were at first. I found it necessary therefore, to
            read the articles of war, and I punished James Proctor, the corporal of marines, who had
            not only quitted his station, and insulted the officer, but struck the Master at Arms
            such a blow as brought him to the ground.</p>
        <p>The next day, [day Wednes. 8] I sent a party up the country to cut wood, and they met
            with some of the natives, who treated them with great kindness and hospitality. Several
            of these friendly Indians came on board in our boat, and seemed, both by their dress and
            behaviour, to be of a superior rank. To these people I paid a particular attention, and
            to discover what present would most gratify them, I laid down before them a Johannes, a
            guinea, a crown piece, a Spanish dollar, a few shillings, some new halfpence, and two
            large nails, making signs that they should take what they liked best. The nails were
            first seized, with great eagerness, and then a few of the halfpence, but the silver and
            gold lay neglected. Having presented them, therefore, with some nails and halfpence, I
            sent them on shore superlatively happy.</p>
        <pb id="461"/>
        <p>From this time, our market was very ill supplied, [day Wednes. 8] the Indians refusing to
            sell provisions at the usual price, and making signs for large nails. It was now thought
            necessary to look more diligently about the ship, to discover what nails had been drawn;
            and it was soon found that all the belaying cleats had been ripped off, and that there
            was scarcely one of the hammock nails left. All hands were now ordered up, and I
            practised every artifice I could think of to discover the thieves, but without success.
            I then told them that till the thieves were discovered, not a single man should go on
            shore: this however produced no effect, except that Proctor, the corporal, behaved in a
            mutinous manner, for which he was instantly punished.</p>
        <p>On Saturday the 11th, [day Saturday 11] in the afternoon, the gunner came on board with a
            tall woman, who seemed to be about five and forty years of age, of a pleasing
            countenance and ma|jestic deportment. He told me that she was but just come into that
            part of the country, and that seeing great respect paid her by the rest of the natives,
            he had made her some presents; in return for which she had invited him to her house,
            which was about two miles up the valley, and given him some large hogs; after which she
            returned with him to the watering-place, and expressed a desire to go on board the ship,
            in which he had thought it proper, on all accounts, that she should be gratified. She
            seemed to be under no restraint, either from diffidence or fear, when she first came
            into the ship; and she behaved, all the while she was on board, with an easy freedom,
            that always distinguishes con|scious superiority and habitual command. I gave her a
            large blue mantle, that reached from her shoulders to her feet, which I threw over her,
            and tied on with ribands; I gave her also a looking-glass, beads of several sorts, and
            many other things, of which she accepted with a very good <pb id="462"/>grace, [day
            Saturday 11] and much pleasure. She took notice that I had been ill, and pointed to the
            shore. I understood that she meant I should go thither to perfect my recovery, and I
            made signs that I would go thither the next morning. When she inti|mated an inclination
            to return, I ordered the gunner to go with her, who, having set her on shore, attended
            her to her habitation, which he described as being very large and well built. He said,
            that in this house she had many guards and domesticks, and that she had another at a
            little distance, which was enclosed in lattice-work.</p>
        <p>The next morning I went on shore for the first time, [day Sunday 12] and my princess, or
            rather queen, for such by her authority she appeared to be, soon after came to me,
            followed by many of her attendants. As she perceived that my disorder had left me very
            weak, she ordered her people to take me in their arms, and carry me not only over the
            river, but all the way to her house; and observing that some of the people who were with
            me, particularly the First Lieutenant and Purser, had also been sick, she caused them
            also to be carried in the same manner, and a guard, which I had ordered out upon the
            occasion, followed. In our way, a vast multitude crouded about us, but upon her waving
            her hand, without speaking a word, they withdrew, and left us a free passage. When we
            approached near her house, a great number of both sexes came out to meet her: these she
            presented to me, after having intimated by signs that they were her relations, and
            taking hold of my hand, she made them kiss it. We then entered the house, which covered
            a piece of ground 327 feet long, and 42 feet broad. It consisted of a roof, thatched
            with palm leaves, and raised upon 39 pillars on each side, and 14 in the middle. The
            ridge of the thatch, on the inside, was 30 feet high, and the sides of the house, to the
            edge of the roof, were 12 feet high; all below the <pb id="463"/>roof being open. As
            soon as we entered the house, [day Sunday 12] she made us sit down, and then calling
            four young girls, she assisted them to take off my shoes, draw down my stockings, and
            pull off my coat, and then directed them to smooth down the skin, and gently chafe it
            with their hands: the same operation was also performed upon the First Lieutenant and
            the Purser, but upon none of those who appeared to be in health. While this was doing,
            our Surgeon, who had walked till he was very warm, took off his wig to cool and refresh
            himself: a sudden exclamation of one of the Indians who saw it, drew the attention of
            the rest, and in a moment every eye was fixed upon the prodigy, and every operation was
            suspended: the whole assembly stood some time motion|less, in silent astonishment, which
            could not have been more strongly expressed if they had discovered that our friend's
            limbs had been screwed on to the trunk; in a short time, however, the young women who
            were chafing us, resumed their employment, and having continued it for about half an
            hour, they dressed us again, but in this they were, as may easily be imagined, very
            aukward; I found great bene|fit, however, from the chafing, and so did the Lieutenant
            and Purser. After a little time, our generous benefactress ordered some bales of Indian
            cloth to be brought out, with which she clothed me, and all that were with me,
            accord|ing to the fashion of the country. At first I declined the ac|ceptance of this
            favour, but being unwilling not to seem pleased with what was intended to please me, I
            acquiesced. When we went away, she ordered a very large sow, big with young, to be taken
            down to the boat, and accompanied us thither herself. She had given directions to her
            people to carry me, as they had done when I came, but as I chose rather to walk, she
            took me by the arm, and whenever we came to a plash of water or dirt, she lifted me over
            with as <pb id="464"/>little trouble as it would have cost me to have lifted over a
            child if I had been well.</p>
        <p>The next morning I sent her by the gunner, [day Monday 13] six hatchets, six bill-hooks,
            and several other things; and when he re|turned, he told me that he found her giving an
            entertain|ment to a great number of people, which, he supposed, could not be less than a
            thousand. The messes were all brought to her by the servants that prepared them, the
            meat being put into the shells of cocoa nuts, and the shells into wooden trays, somewhat
            like those used by our but|chers, and she distributed them with her own hands to the
            guests, who were seated in rows round the great house. When this was done, she sat down
            herself, upon a place somewhat elevated above the rest, and two women, placing
            themselves one on each side of her, fed her, she opening her mouth as they brought their
            hands up with the food. When she saw the gunner, she ordered a mess for him; he could
            not certainly tell what it was, but he believed it to be fowl picked small, with apples
            cut among it, and seasoned with salt water; it was, however, very well tasted. She
            ac|cepted the things that I sent her, and seemed to be much pleased with them. After
            this correspondence was esta|blished with the queen, provisions of every kind became
            much more plenty at market; but though fowls and hogs were every day brought in, we were
            still obliged to pay more for them than at the first, the market having been spoiled by
            the nails which our men had stolen and given to the women; I therefore gave orders that
            every man should be searched before he went on shore, and that no woman should be
            suffered to cross the river.</p>
        <p>On the 14th, [day Tuesday 14] the gunner being on shore to trade, per|ceived an old woman
            on the other side of the river, weeping <pb id="465"/>bitterly: [day Tuesday 14] when
            she saw that she had drawn his attention upon her, she sent a young man, who stood by
            her, over the river to him, with a branch of the plantain tree in his hand. When he came
            up, he made a long speech, and then laid down his bough at the gunner's feet: after this
            he went back and brought over the old woman, another man at the same time bringing over
            two large fat hogs. The woman looked round upon our people with great attention, fixing
            her eyes sometimes upon one, and sometimes upon another, and at last burst into tears.
            The young man who brought her over the river, perceiving the gunner's concern and
            astonishment, made another speech, longer than the first: still, however, the woman's
            distress was a mystery, but at length she made him understand that her husband, and
            three of her sons, had been killed in the attack of the ship. During this explanation,
            she was to affected that at last she sunk down unable to speak, and the two young men,
            who endeavoured to support her, appeared to be nearly in the same condition: they were
            probably two more of her sons, or some very near relations. The gunner did all in his
            power to sooth and comfort her, and when she had in some measure recovered her
            recollection, she ordered the two hogs to be delivered to him, and gave him her hand in
            token of friendship, but would accept nothing in return, though he offered her ten times
            as much as would have purchased the hogs at market.</p>
        <p>The next morning, I sent the Second Lieutenant, [day Wednes. 15] with all the boats, and
            sixty men, to the westward, to look at the coun|try, and try what was to be got. About
            noon he returned, having marched along the shore near six miles. He found the country
            very pleasant and populous, and abounding as well with hogs and fowls, as fruit, and
            other vegetables of various kinds. The inhabitants offered him no molestation, <pb
                id="466"/>but did not seem willing to part with any of the provisions which our
            people were most desirous to purchase: [day Wednes. 15] they gave them, however, a few
            cocoa-nuts and plantains, and at length sold them nine hogs and a few fowls. The
            Lieu|tenant was of opinion, that they might be brought to trade freely by degrees, but
            the distance from the ship was so great, that too many men would be necessary for a
            guard. He saw a great number of very large canoes upon the beach, and some that were
            building. He observed that all their tools were made of stone, shells, and bone, and
            very justly inferred, that they had no metal of any kind. He found no quadrupeds among
            them, besides hogs and dogs, nor any earthen vessel, so that all their food is either
            baked or roasted. Having no vessel in which water could be subjected to the action of
            fire, they had no more idea that it could be made hot, than that it could be made solid.
            As the queen was one morning at breakfast with us on board the ship, one of her
            attendants, a man of some note, and one of those that we thought were priests, saw the
            Surgeon fill the tea|pot by turning the cock of an urn that stood upon the table: having
            remarked this with great curiosity and attention, he presently turned the cock, and
            received the water upon his hand: as soon as he felt himself scalded, he roared out, and
            began to dance about the cabbin with the most extravagant and ridiculous expressions of
            pain and astonishment: the other Indians, not being able to conceive what was the
            mat|ter with him, stood staring at him in amaze, and not with|out some mixture of
            terror. The Surgeon, however, who had innocently been the cause of the mischief, applied
            a re|medy, though it was some time before the poor fellow was easy.</p>
        <p>On Thursday the 16th, [day Thursday 16] Mr. Furneaux, my Second Lieu|tenant, was taken
            very ill, which distressed me greatly, as <pab id="467"/>the First Lieutenant was not
            yet recovered, [day Thursday 16] and I was still in a very weak state myself: I was this
            day also obliged once more to punish Proctor, the corporal of marines, for muti|nous
            behaviour. The queen had now been absent several days, but the natives made us
            understand, by signs, that the next day she would be with us again.</p>
        <p>Accordingly the next morning she came down to the beach, and soon after a great number of
            people, [day Friday 17] whom we had never seen before, brought to market provisions of
            every kind; and the gunner sent off fourteen hogs, and fruit in great plenty.</p>
        <p>In the afternoon of the next day, [day Saturday 18] the queen came on board, with a
            present of two large hogs, for she never con|descended to barter, and in the evening she
            returned on shore. I sent a present with her, by the Master, and as soon as they landed,
            she took him by the hand, and having made a long speech to she people that flocked round
            them, she led him to her house, where she clothed him, as she had before done me,
            according to the fashion of the country.</p>
        <p>The next morning, [day Sunday 19] he sent off a greater quantity of stock than we had
            ever procured in one day before; it consisted of forty-eight hogs and pigs, four dozen
            of fowls, with bread-fruit, bananas, apples, and cocoa-nuts, almost without number.</p>
        <p>On the 20th, we continued to trade with good success, [day Monday 20] but in the
            afternoon it was discovered that Francis Pinckney, one of the seamen, had drawn the
            cleats to which the main sheet was belayed, and, after stealing the spikes, thrown them
            over board. Having secured the offender, I called all the people together upon the deck,
            and after taking some pains to explain his crime, with all its aggravations, I ordered
            that he should be whipped with nettles while he ran <pb id="468"/>the gauntlet thrice
            round the deck: [day Monday 20] my rhetoric, however, had very little effect, for most
            of the crew being equally cri|minal with himself, he was handled so tenderly, that
            others were rather encouraged to repeat the offence by the hope of impunity, than
            deterred by the fear of punishment. To preserve the ship, therefore, from being pulled
            to pieces, and the price of refreshments from being raised so high as soon to exhaust
            our articles of trade, I ordered that no man, except the wooders and waterers, with
            their guard, should be permitted to go on shore.</p>
        <p>On the 21st, [day Tuesday 21] the queen came again on board, and brought several large
            hogs as a present, for which, as usual, she would accept of no return. When she was
            about to leave the ship, she expressed a desire that I should go on shore with her, to
            which I consented, taking several of the officers with me. When we arrived at her house,
            she made us all sit down, and taking off my hat, she tied to it a bunch or tuft of
            feathers of various colours, such as I had seen no person on shore wear but herself,
            which produced by no means a disagreeable effect. She also tied round my hat, and the
            hats of those who were with me, wreaths of braided or plaited hair, and gave us to
            understand that both the hair and workmanship were her own: she also presented us with
            some matts, that were very curiously wrought. In the eve|ning she accompanied us back to
            the beach, and when we were getting into the boat, she put on board a fine large sow,
            big with young, and a great quantity of fruit. As we were parting, I made signs that I
            should quit the island in seven days: she immediately comprehended my meaning, and made
            signs that I should stay twenty days; that I should go two days journey into the
            country, stay there a few days, bring down plenty of hogs and poultry, and after that
            leave the island. I again made signs that I must go in seven days; <pb id="469"/>upon
            which she burst into tears, and it was not without great difficulty that she was
            pacified.</p>
        <p>The next morning, [day Wednes. 22] the gunner sent off no less than twenty hogs, with
            great plenty of fruit. Our decks were now quite full of hogs and poultry, of which we
            killed only the small ones, and kept the others for sea stores; we found, how|ever, to
            our great mortification, that neither the fowls nor the hogs could, without great
            difficulty, be brought to eat any thing but fruit, which made it necessary to kill them
            faster than we should otherwise have done: two, however, a boar and a sow, were brought
            alive to England, of which I made a present to Mr. Stephens, Secretary to the Admiralty;
            the sow afterwards died in pigging, but the boar is still alive.</p>
        <p>On the 23d, we had very heavy rain, [day Thursday 23] with a storm of wind that blew down
            several trees on shore, though very little of it was felt where the ship lay.</p>
        <p>The next day, I sent the old man, [day Friday 24] who had been of great service to the
            gunner at the market-tent, another iron pot, some hatchets and bills, and a piece of
            cloth. I also sent the queen two turkies, two geese, three Guinea hens, a cat big with
            kitten, some china, looking-glasses, glass bottles, shirts, needles, thread, cloth,
            ribands, peas, some small white kidney beans, called callivances, and about sixteen
            different sorts of garden seeds, and a shovel, besides a con|siderable quantity of
            cutlery wares, consisting of knives, scissars, bill-hooks, and other things. We had
            already planted several sorts of the garden seeds, and some peas in several places, and
            had the pleasure to see them come up in a very flourishing state, yet there were no
            remains of them when Captain Cook left the island. I sent her also two iron pots, and a
            few spoons. In return for these things, the gun|ner brought off eighteen hogs, and some
            fruit.</p>
        <pb id="470"/>
        <p>In the morning of the 25th, [day Saturday 25] I ordered Mr. Gore, one of the mates, with
            all the marines, forty seamen, and four midshipmen, to go up the valley by the river as
            high as they could, and examine the soil and produce of the country, noting the trees
            and plants which they should find, and when they saw any stream from the mountains, to
            trace it to its source, and observe whether it was tinctured with any mineral or ore. I
            cautioned them also to keep continually upon their guard against the natives, and
            directed them to make a fire, as a signal, if they should be attacked. At the same time,
            I took a guard on shore, and erected a tent on a point of land, to observe an eclipse of
            the sun, which, the morning being very clear, was done with great accuracy. The
            immersion began, by true time, at 6 hours 51 minutes 50 seconds. The emersion, by true
            time, was at 8 hours 1 minute 0 seconds. The duration of the eclipse was 1 hour 9
            minutes 10 seconds. The latitude of the point, on which the observation was made, was
            17° 30′ S. the sun's declination was 19° 40′ N. and the variation of the needle 5° 36′
            E.</p>
        <p>After the observation was taken, I went to the queen's house, and shewed her the
            telescope, which was a reflector. After she had admired its structure, I endeavoured to
            make her comprehend its use, and fixing it so as to command several distant objects,
            with which she was well acquainted, but which could not be distinguished with the naked
            eye, I made her look through it. As soon as the saw them, she started back with
            astonishment, and directing her eye as the glass was pointed, stood some time motionless
            and silent; she then looked through the glass again, and again sought in vain, with the
            naked eye, for the objects which it disco|vered. As they by turns vanished and
            re-appeared, her <pb id="471"/>countenance and gestures expressed a mixture of wonder
            and delight which no language can describe. [day Saturday 25] When the glass was
            removed, I invited her, and several of the Chiefs that were with her, to go with me on
            board the ship, in which I had a view to the security of the party that I had sent out;
            for I thought that while the queen, and the prin|cipal people were known to be in my
            power, nothing would be attempted against any person belonging to the ship on shore.
            When we got on board, I ordered a good dinner for their entertainment, but the queen
            would neither eat nor drink; the people that were with her eat very heartily of whatever
            was set before them, but would drink only plain water.</p>
        <p>In the evening our people returned from their excursion, and came down to the beach, upon
            which I put the queen and her attendants into the boats, and sent them on shore. As she
            was going over the ship's side, she asked, by signs, whether I still persisted in my
            resolution of leaving the island at the time I had fixed; and when I made her understand
            that it was impossible I should stay longer, she expressed her regret by a flood of
            tears, which for a while took away her speech. As soon as her passion subsided, she told
            me that she would come on board again the next day; and thus we parted.</p>
    </body>
</div>
